<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay towards the deciding of the so much and so long controverted case of usury in a problematical paradox discussed, whether it be lawful (and not rather sinful) for any man to borrow meerly to encrease his wealth : as also some animadversions upon the Resolution of the case of usury, by a reverend and very learned doctor / by D.C.</title>
            <author>D. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31719</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13131482</idno>
  <idno type="VID">97861</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240863685</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33296</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13131482</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97861)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1546:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay towards the deciding of the so much and so long controverted case of usury in a problematical paradox discussed, whether it be lawful (and not rather sinful) for any man to borrow meerly to encrease his wealth : as also some animadversions upon the Resolution of the case of usury, by a reverend and very learned doctor / by D.C.</title>
                  <author>D. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Rothwell and are to be sold at the sign of the fountain and bear ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Usury --  Moral and ethical aspects.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Interest.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97861:1"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY TOWARDS The Deciding of the so much, and so long Controverted CASE OF USURY.</p>
            <p>IN A Problematical Paradox, discussed, whether it be lawful (and not rather sinful) for any man to Borrow, meerly to encrease his Wealth.</p>
            <p>As also, some Animadversions upon the Resolution of the Case of Usury, by a Reverend, and very Learned Doctor.</p>
            <p>By <hi>D. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 28.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that by usury and unjust gain encreaseth his substance, he shall gather it for him that will pity the poor.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 15.1, 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Lord, who shall abide in thy Tabernacle? who shall dwell in thy holy Hill? He that putteth not out his money to usury.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luk. 6.35.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Do good and lend, looking for nothing again; and your reward shall be great, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Rothwell,</hi> and are to be sold at the sign of the Fountain and Bear in <hi>Cheap-side.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97861:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97861:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Consciencious READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat my Judgement formerly was' and now is, concerning the Case propounded, I shall not much scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to discover to the <hi>Reader,</hi> to the World: whiles I was young and low in Estate, not furnished with <hi>Tools</hi> for the Trade of <hi>Ʋsury</hi> (though I bless God, as I had no ability to <hi>Lend,</hi> so had I no great need to <hi>Borrow</hi>) I was in my Judgement against all <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> (as I believe, most in that condition are: none but either <hi>Prodigals</hi> or <hi>Proud</hi> persons, would borrow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> if they might borrow freely:) but when, by the blessing of God, I came to be <hi>Master</hi> of a little Money lying by me, new thoughts, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>temptations</hi> began to molest me; For on the one side, I thought a <hi>Talent,</hi> though little, should not lye idle, but be improved: on the other, I was told by some <hi>Casuists,</hi> that amongst other persons, <hi>Ʋsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> was permitted to <hi>Ministers</hi> or <hi>Scholars,</hi> who are not allowed, or want <hi>skill</hi> to drive any secular
<pb facs="tcp:97861:3"/> Trade: and by some not meanly both learned, and <hi>pious</hi> men, that to lend to <hi>wealthy</hi> men, leaving it free to the Borrower, to give what profit he please, without any <hi>compact,</hi> was very lawful: Hereupon I was too easily perswaded to venture on this way, yet but a <hi>little,</hi> and for a <hi>little time;</hi> for finding so much said against <hi>Ʋsury</hi> in Scripture, and by men of all Nations and Professions, I could not satisfie my Conscience with the way: and therefore I recall'd my <hi>Money,</hi> with the loss of the <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> or Gain of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered me. This put me upon further study of the <hi>Case,</hi> which, at vacant times from other more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary businesses of my calling, I have more or less, prosecuted, I think well nigh these thirty years past; and after all the <hi>disquisition</hi> I could make, have not found, where to fix the foot of my <hi>Conscience,</hi> for the lawfulness of it: but rather, by the <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of the Arguments for it, the nicety of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions upon it, and the multitude of <hi>Cautions</hi> about it, very difficult, if not impossible to be due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly observed, I thought it rather unlawful, or at least so <hi>doubtful,</hi> that I took the safer way; as not to borrow without great need, so nor to lend to any that needed not (no not without <hi>Ʋsury</hi>) unless in <hi>Cases</hi> hereafter <hi>cautioned,</hi> in the Probleme it self.</p>
            <p>All that hath been said hitherto, by learned and pious men, (as I have observed) against <hi>lending upon Ʋsury,</hi> hath not made scarce one professed <hi>Ʋsurer</hi> less; but rather confirmed some, and increased more, by their <hi>condescensions</hi> in the <hi>Case:</hi> For whilst they yeeld, Usury in some Cases, may lawfully be taken of the rich,<note place="margin">Lucrum cessans, aut damnum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergens.</note> as 1. in case of <hi>loss</hi> of gain the <hi>Lender</hi> might have made, had his Money been
<pb facs="tcp:97861:3"/> in his own hand (to say nothing of the <hi>gain</hi> of loss, for want of his Money.) And 2. when the rich Borrower gains by the use of the Money: now rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son will come in, and plead, <hi>Ʋsury</hi> is very equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: as being injurious to neither party. But they do not consider, that these <hi>Cautions</hi> may be as equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, when they lend to a <hi>needier</hi> man: for as on the one side, he may get gain by the borrowed; so on the other, the <hi>Lender</hi> may sustain <hi>loss,</hi> whiles another hath his Money: and so all <hi>Ʋsury</hi> almost, may be lawful. But of this more in a more proper place.</p>
            <p>So much labor then being lost upō the <hi>Lenders,</hi> we must try, whether we can prevail any better, with the <hi>Borrowers:</hi> for if there were no Borrowers upon Usury, there would be no Lenders: and contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if there were no Lenders upon Usury, there could be no Borrowers; and till mens <hi>Consciences</hi> be convinced of the unlawfulness of Usury, both in taking and giving, and in <hi>giving,</hi> as well (though perhaps not so much) as in <hi>taking;</hi> it will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to suppress <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> or to regulate them in the Case. For let <hi>States</hi> make what Laws they can, against <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> either wholly to suppress it, or to <hi>confine</hi> and limit it, <hi>Ʋsurers,</hi> with the concurrence of some <hi>Borrowers,</hi> will evade, and elude them all, by secret underhand contracts, <hi>&amp;c. Salmasius,</hi> the stoutest Champion for <hi>Ʋsurers,</hi> tells us, and I think,<note place="margin">See Jer. 15.16</note> truly: <q>[That Foenoration, if it be a sin, is a sin of both parties, the Borrower as well as the Lender:]</q> And to make out this, I have a whole <hi>Chapter,</hi> in a larger discourse: But I say further,</p>
            <p>My present <hi>undertaking</hi> is far harder, to perswade
<pb facs="tcp:97861:4"/> men to two <hi>paradoxal</hi> truths. 1. That it is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlawful for men, that are not <hi>Needy,</hi> to borrow upon Usury, but to <hi>borrow at all,</hi> except in case of a just necessity. 2. To perswade <hi>rich</hi> men, that they are bound, as not to <hi>lend</hi> to any, but the <hi>needy,</hi> so to lend to the <hi>needy</hi> freely: and then there will be no Usury found. How hard a task I have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, the success will prove. I do not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the <hi>Case</hi> to other mens Consciences, but only tender this as an <hi>Essay,</hi> to give the learned, and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious in this Controversie an occasion to discusse the Point, to some further issue: entreating them, that if they approve hereof, they will <hi>signifie</hi> so much to me, or my <hi>Stationer,</hi> which may encourage me to publish a larger and fuller Discourse on this <hi>intricate</hi> Subject: if they approve not of my way, and will modestly <hi>convince</hi> me privately, or by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of their Reasons, I shall either publickly acknowledge it, if I be convinced, or very <hi>modestly</hi> reply, to discover further the truth of the Case, if I be not convinced, Farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:97861:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here hath been a <hi>question</hi> sometimes started amongst men (of no great <hi>moment,</hi> or <hi>diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty,</hi> (I confesse) <q>[What profession or calling of common life, was the most Ancient?] And that is easily resolved; The <hi>Gardiner</hi> in <hi>Adam</hi> himself; and then, the <hi>Husbandman,</hi> and <hi>Shepherd,</hi> in his two Sons; [<hi>Abel</hi> was a keeper of sheep,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.2.</note> and <hi>Cain</hi> was a tiller of the ground.] The question were better put, [Which of the many professions now, is the most innocent, and freest from doing wrong?]</q> The Solution whereof will be more difficult: for since the time that Man <hi>corrupted</hi> himself, and got too much of the <hi>Subtilty</hi> of the Serpent, all <hi>Trades,</hi> more or less, have been corrupted; and are grown, from their pristine <hi>Simplicity,</hi> to be called <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries;</hi> I fear too often, <hi>Mysteries</hi> of Iniquity: Even one of the most ancient, and most <hi>simple,</hi> hath long ago been complained of, as full of fraud and oppression, <hi>Amos 8.4, 5, 6.</hi> and more generally, <hi>Jerem. 5.26, 27.</hi> Hence are those many and difficult <hi>Cases</hi> of Conscience, discussed by Learned Men, about <hi>gain taken in Trading,</hi> and after long disputes, its left to <hi>Conscience</hi> it self, to make the
<pb facs="tcp:97861:5"/> Determination. Amongst other Callings, a <hi>Wise Man</hi> (but not so wise as <hi>Solomon,</hi> whom some would make the <hi>Authour</hi> of the Book) hath given his observation of two, that in his experience, were too prone to offend: <q>[A Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant cannot lightly keep himself from <hi>Wrong,</hi> and a Victualler is not free from sin, <hi>Eccles. 26.30.</hi>]</q> The former failing often, by <hi>Monopolizing, Engrossing, Fore-taking,</hi> and making a scarcity, in plenty, &amp;c. The other of false <hi>Measures,</hi> excessive <hi>prizes,</hi> and being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of other mens sins, of <hi>Riot, Drunkennesse,</hi> and other abominations.</p>
            <p>Amongst the many <hi>grievances</hi> and complaints, in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Comerce,</hi> or Trading, none is more <hi>Ancient,</hi> none more <hi>difficult</hi> to resolve, than that of <hi>Usury,</hi> the Subject of this present Discourse: Ancient it is, for, besides the <hi>Scripture,</hi> where it was prohibited early, and yet practis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it was controverted amongst the <hi>Heathens</hi> of old, and decryed by men of severall <hi>professions,</hi> in all succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ages to this day, <hi>Philosophers, Polititians, Lawyers, Divines,</hi> &amp;c. The Difficulty appears, in that the <hi>patronage</hi> thereof, is undertaken by Learned, and some <hi>pious</hi> men: and the <hi>Case</hi> not yet decided to most Mens <hi>Satisfactions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Causes</hi> of the difficulty of Decision of the <hi>Case,</hi> seem to me (after some tryall and observation) to be these, or some of these: <hi>1.</hi> The different <hi>Judgements</hi> of the Learned about the Explication of the <hi>Nature</hi> and quality of those <hi>Original Lawes</hi> concerning Ʋsury, <hi>Exod. 22.25. Levit. 25.36. Deut. 23.19.</hi> viz. Whether they were <hi>Morall,</hi> and so concerned all Nations, or <hi>Judiciall,</hi> and so concerned onely the <hi>Jewes:</hi> or mixt, as partly <hi>Morall,</hi> and partly <hi>Judiciall:</hi> and so partly in force, and partly void. <hi>2.</hi> The <hi>New Distinctions</hi> raised upon these
<pb facs="tcp:97861:5"/> Texts; as amongst others, these, (to omit those old ones, of <hi>poore</hi> and <hi>rich:</hi> of <hi>biting</hi> and <hi>helping</hi> Ʋsury) <hi>1.</hi> Ʋsury by <hi>compact,</hi> and Ʋsury without any <hi>compact: e. gr.</hi> If a Man lend his money to a rich wealthy <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,</hi> upon bond, not specifying, nor requiring any use, this they hold lawfull; and this was the Judgement and Practice, (they say) of many very Learned and <hi>pious</hi> Men: wherein, I doubt, there was this <hi>double deceit;</hi> First that there was in it, <hi>mentall</hi> Ʋsury (which themselves condemned) appearing sometimes by this, that if an <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus</hi> of gaine was not tendred, they <hi>grumbled</hi> at it, and would presently call in their money. Secondly, that they thought it lawful to lend to <hi>Rich</hi> men, that had no <hi>need</hi> to borrow (which is the thing, I shall endeavour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute:) for had they lent it to <hi>needy</hi> men freely, it had been truly commendable; themselves having no <hi>power</hi> to use it, and as they made shew, no great <hi>need,</hi> or <hi>care</hi> to improve it. <hi>2.</hi> They distinguished the <hi>manner</hi> of lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their money, either as <hi>Meat,</hi> and Victuals, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently eaten and consumed; Or as <hi>Merchandise</hi> to trade with: the first utterly unlawful: the second lawfull, but this also is subject to this exception, (besides others) that a poor or <hi>needy</hi> man, may borrow money as <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandise,</hi> to keep up his Trade; and yet the <hi>Lawes,</hi> as they make no such <hi>distinction,</hi> in a poor mans borrowing, so they allow no Ʋsury to be taken of him, however he use it, of which more largely hereafter. <hi>3.</hi> Another cause of the difficulty and <hi>doubtfulnesse</hi> of Ʋsury, was the <hi>prescrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of so many <hi>Cautions,</hi> for the Lender, for the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower, and the manner of lending upon Ʋsury; which are very hard to be remembred, and will hardlier be observed by the <hi>Usurer;</hi> if Grave, Learned, and <hi>Pious</hi> men, will but say, <hi>Usury</hi> is in any case lawful. <hi>4.</hi> The difficulty
<pb facs="tcp:97861:6"/> is increased, by the <hi>Casuists</hi> propounding so many <hi>Cases</hi> of Contracts, very like to <hi>Usury,</hi> (and sometimes as bad or worse) and yet confessed lawful: The instances are well known to those, that are versed in this Controversie, and largely spoken to else where. Lastly, another Cause is, that Learned Men are not agreed upon the <hi>Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Ʋsury; some give one, some another, and each rather labouring to confute others Definitions, than able to maintain his own: as it is easier <hi>to pull down</hi> an house than to build it.</p>
            <p>And yet, notwithstanding these seeming <hi>difficulties,</hi> as some men <hi>resolve,</hi> and expound the former originall Texts, the <hi>Resolution</hi> of the Case, and the <hi>Definition</hi> of Ʋsury is easie to be made; For <hi>1.</hi> Some make those Laws to be <hi>Judiciall,</hi> and so to concern only the <hi>Jewish</hi> Politie: <hi>and then the Definition of Usury was this <q>[Usury is increase, or gain taken for lending to a Brother a Jew]</q>
               </hi> which is seemingly at least confirmed by this, that <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury</hi> was by God permitted to be taken of any stranger of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations. Both which if they be true, the Case is easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decided, the Judiciall Law being annulled, all <hi>Usury</hi> is <hi>lawfull,</hi> in lending to poor or rich: So concludes the Learned <hi>Salmasius;</hi> So the <hi>Authour</hi> of <hi>Quaestio quodlibetica,</hi> and his <hi>Publisher,</hi> and others, though (with their good leave I speak it) they sometimes contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict themselves, denying it <hi>lawful</hi> to the poor. <hi>2.</hi> Some again, make the Lawes (at least in part) <hi>Moral,</hi> viz. with respect to the <hi>needy,</hi> instanced in all the Lawes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly, or by necessary consequence; and then the <hi>Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is clear; <q>
                  <hi>[Usury is gain taken for lending to the poor]</hi>
               </q> and the Case easily determined: Ʋsury is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully taken of the poor, but lawful when we lend to the rich. This is the ordinary <hi>Resolution</hi> of the Case. But yet some
<pb facs="tcp:97861:6"/> scruples may arise, even in this way: both that it will be hard to resolve, who is <hi>poor,</hi> or <hi>rich,</hi> because, as the wisest man sayes, <q>[<hi>There is one that is poor, and maketh himself rich: and there is another that is rich, and makes himself poor,</hi>]</q> &amp; also, because in some cases, they yeeld Ʋsury may be sinfull, if taken of the rich, and sometimes lawfully taken of the poor, and more, else where specified: which may perswade <hi>tender consciences,</hi> not to medle with <hi>lending on Usury</hi> at all, rather than to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the <hi>perplexities</hi> arising from it: especially, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so many tother lawful <hi>ways</hi> to improve their money.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore the first way, to <hi>take Usury</hi> of all, is both too loose, and <hi>uncharitable</hi> and the other too <hi>thorny</hi> and perplexed with so many <hi>distinctions</hi> and <hi>cautions:</hi> what is to be resolved on, in this case? To assert, that <hi>all Usury is unlawful,</hi> at first sight, will seem to rich <hi>trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and well monyed man, not onely a <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox,</hi> but a very <hi>Heterodox</hi> opinion; and as some have told mee, the way to destroy all <hi>Merchandizing,</hi> and Trading: for as the <hi>Merchant</hi> (say they) cannot traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick without borrowing upon <hi>Usury:</hi> so nor can other <hi>trades</hi> goe on, or subsist, without <hi>Selling</hi> for day, at a dearer rate, which is, say some, to sell that which is none of their own, viz. <hi>Time;</hi> and no other, no better than <hi>Usury:</hi> some of those, who are <hi>patrons</hi> of some <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts,</hi> esteemed by others, to be Ʋsurious, do roundly as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert <q>[That all Usury is unlawful, but all lending for gain, is not Usurious.]</q> But, under favour, this seemes a <hi>contradiction</hi> to the true <hi>definition</hi> of Ʋsury: for if Ʋsury be rightly defined <q>[a gain taken for lending;]</q> then all lending for gain is <hi>Usurious;</hi> the definition, and the thing defined, being convertible, as all <hi>Logicians</hi> know: the truth is, as I said, that the controversie is made so difficult for want of an agreement
<pb facs="tcp:97861:7"/> in the <hi>definition</hi> of Ʋsury: if that were fixed, and assent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, the business were quickly ended: now the <hi>definition</hi> must be collected, not out of private mens <hi>fancies,</hi> but out of the <hi>original texts,</hi> that prohibite Ʋsury: and it seems strange to mee, that any man rational should assert, that there is no definition of Ʋsury given in, or to be collected out of Scripture; for then (to add no more now) how should the <hi>Jews</hi> be able to observe those laws, if they did not clearly know, what the <hi>Usury</hi> was, which was forbidden them: And besides, if those Laws were <hi>Judicial,</hi> as <hi>some,</hi> to concern onely the <hi>Jews;</hi> or <hi>moral,</hi> as others, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern all <hi>poor</hi> onely, the definitions were easily gathered, as was said afore, and there expressed. The several definitions given by several men, are else where discussed, and all,<note place="margin">Lucrum ex mutuo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum.</note> but one, discovered <hi>imperfect,</hi> and unsatisfying: the old and common definition, is that, which, I think, comes neerest to the truth, and scripture-texts: [Ʋsury is gain covenanted for lending:] and each pirticular ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient is to be found there. <hi>1.</hi> It is a gain, called in one text, increase. <hi>2.</hi> For lending; when thou lendest. <hi>3.</hi> Covenanted or compacted for; thou shalt not impose or lay upon him Ʋsury: and its added, nor <hi>take it</hi> of him; which thou canst not well require, without a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> explicite, or implicite. If any say, your definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wants one thing expressed, or implyed in all the three texts, that is the <hi>needy,</hi> who is the borrower; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, its needless to add that, in the definition, which is perfect without it; as included in the word <hi>lending,</hi> which as it is an act of <hi>charity,</hi> or <hi>courtesie,</hi> supposes the <hi>borrower</hi> to be needy, and in some necessity to borrow: and consequently excludes all others from borrowing; and then, <hi>borrowing</hi> and <hi>lending</hi> being <hi>Relata,</hi> if it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for men in no necessity, to <hi>borrow,</hi> it will prove al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
<pb facs="tcp:97861:7"/> unlawful to lend to such at all: and so there can be no <hi>Usury.</hi> This indeed is the <hi>mark</hi> I aim at, and hope to hit: more largely discussed else where: at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, to make it appear <hi>feazable,</hi> and probable, I say onely thus much; that if it be lawfull to lend to the <hi>rich,</hi> which have no need to borrow, it seems to mee, that thereupon it will follow, that Ʋsury for <hi>Lending</hi> may lawfully be taken of all, poor as well as rich, in some cases; Reasons of equity and justice will be pleaded in both; as <hi>1.</hi> When the <hi>Borrower</hi> gets well by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney lent. <hi>2.</hi> When the lender is damaged for want of his money, by Lucrum cessans, or Damnum emergens; which may happen in <hi>lending</hi> to the <hi>poor</hi> and needie; he may gain well by the money lent: and the lender may suffer, for want of his money: therefore say some, <hi>gain</hi> may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be taken of poor &amp; rich: on the other side, some are so charitable as to deny <hi>Usury</hi> to be lawfully taken of the rich, when either he gets nothing, or loses by the mony lent, though it might have concern'd the <hi>lender,</hi> to have had his money in his own hand: others are not so <hi>mercifully</hi> minded: I forbear to say any more; having at large spoken of it, in another place: I onely desire it might be observed, that instead of the word <hi>poor,</hi> which in our language in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports one neerer unto <hi>beggery,</hi> I use the word <hi>needy,</hi> (the original word signifying one <hi>afflicted</hi> with any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity) wch may extend to the <hi>rich</hi> sometimes, who may have just <hi>need</hi> to borrow, <hi>as well,</hi> though perhaps, not as <hi>much,</hi> as the poorer sort; and in such cases, I allow thē both to <hi>borrow,</hi> and to be <hi>lent</hi> unto; the one in <hi>cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie,</hi> the other in <hi>charity,</hi> but both <hi>freely,</hi> without any Ʋsury.</p>
            <p>To make way then, for the further discovery of my
<pb facs="tcp:97861:8"/> judgement in the <hi>Case</hi> of <hi>Usury,</hi> &amp; for the discussing of the <hi>problem</hi> propounded in the title page; I shall lay down my thoughts in these five following <hi>Theorems,</hi> the first onely to be discoursed of, by way of <hi>essay,</hi> at present. viz.</p>
            <q>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1. None may lawfully borrow, but the</hi> Needie.</item>
                  <item>2. No man is <hi>bound</hi> to lend to any, but the <hi>Needie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. To the <hi>Needie,</hi> an able man is bound to lend.</item>
                  <item>4. When he lends to the <hi>Needie,</hi> he must lend freely.</item>
                  <item>5. A man is bound not to lend to such, as are not <hi>Needy.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <p>This way may seem something about, <hi>to</hi> prove <hi>all Usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> unlawful; but if I be not much deceived, it is the surest and neerest way to decide the controversie: If it be not, I desire, with <hi>reason,</hi> to be undeceived. Of the three <hi>middlemost,</hi> I know not, whether any can well make any doubt: the difficulty lies, in proving the first and the last; and the last by the first: And if both be sufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, I doubt not to make good, <hi>[That all Usury for lending, is unlawfull;]</hi> How I performe my <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking</hi> in the first, is now to be judged, by the learned, Judicious and Conscientious <hi>Reader,</hi> to whom I humbly submit all my labours.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97861:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE PROBLEM,</hi> Whether it be lawful (and not rather sinful) for any man to <hi>Borrow,</hi> in no necessity, or meerly to <hi>increase</hi> his wealth?</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I undertake the <hi>Discussion</hi> of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem</hi> or Paradox, I shall, by way of explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, premise these three things, to prevent <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions</hi> in the way.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. The first Lawes speake onely of the needy.</note> That the three first <hi>Laws</hi> concerning <hi>Ʋ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury,</hi> afore named, do all, either expressely, or implicitely, by rational consequence, intend the <hi>Borrower</hi> should be a <hi>Needy</hi> man, and say nothing directly (if at all any thing) of the <hi>Rich</hi> and wealthy; as is evident to him, that <hi>consults,</hi> and seriously considers the texts: whereupon some have peremptorily concluded, that these texts, concern onely the <hi>poore;</hi> and that Usury, was ever <hi>lawful</hi> to be taken of the Rich, forbidden onely to the Needy: but then it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns them to shew some texts in Scripture, that allowed them Usury from the Rich, or some instance there, of any that did lawfully so <hi>practise,</hi> which I believe they cannot do. Some have said, that <hi>Ʋsury</hi> was forbidden, by a <hi>Judicial</hi> Law, to rich and poorer <hi>Jews,</hi> in the word <hi>brother,</hi> opposed to a stranger: which <hi>Judicial</hi> Law, being now void, Usury is lawful, as well from a <hi>rich brother,</hi> as from a stranger: but both these and the former, do forget to take notice, that <hi>Ʋsury</hi> forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97861:9"/> to the <hi>brother</hi> was <hi>Nesher, biting Ʋsury,</hi> and so being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressive, was forbidden both to Jew and Gentile, be they poor or rich: how ever, my assertion is evident, that the <hi>Borrower</hi> in the texts, is held forth to be a <hi>needy</hi> man: whence, one of these things, will be consequent. 1. That either it was <hi>lawful</hi> then to lend upon Usury to <hi>wealthy</hi> men, that borrow not for <hi>need,</hi> but for some other reason, or end, which is both contrary to the judgement, and practice of the <hi>Conscientions Jews,</hi> who lent not upon Usury, to any of their <hi>Brethren</hi> poor or rich (as their <hi>Rabbins</hi> tel us) and also to reason it self, as was hinted before; because <hi>Nesher</hi> being oppressive, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to rich and poor. Or, 2. That God intended, that none but the <hi>needy</hi> should borrow (rich or poor) and that freely without any Usury: who are needy, comes next to be considered; whom we allow to borrow.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Necessity is two fold.</note>2. What we mean by <hi>need,</hi> or <hi>necessity,</hi> will appeare by way of distinction: there is a double necessity,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. Feigned or Forced, by.</note>1. <hi>Feigned</hi> or <hi>forced,</hi> as made by a mans selfe, for ends of his owne, when he needeth not: nor God allowes. And this may arise from many causes, but all may be reduced to two heads, <hi>Prodigality</hi> and <hi>Covetousness,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Prodigality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Prodigality.</note> to spend upon his Lusts, of several kinds, <hi>pride</hi> in Apparel, <hi>vain-glory</hi> in Hous-keeping or Building, <hi>Ryot,</hi> and <hi>Luxury, Intemperance,</hi> and <hi>Incontinencie; Gaming</hi> and the like; of one of these (applyable to all) a wise man gave good counsel; <q>[Become not poor by making banquets of that which thou hast borrowed (on Ʋsury) and so leave nothing in thy purse; else thou shouldst insidiously lie in wait, for thine owne soul (thy life) Ecclus. <hi>18.33,</hi>]</q> Now all, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most, that understand <hi>Reason,</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> consent, that it is unlawfull for such, upon such <hi>ends,</hi> to borrow, or to <hi>lend</hi> to such. And yet these are <hi>Common Ʋsurers</hi> best <hi>Clients,</hi> if they have but sufficient to Pawne or Morgage.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Covetousnes</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</note> to advance his <hi>estate;</hi> to increase in wealth and riches; to load himselfe with <hi>thick clay;</hi> to purchase <hi>Mannors</hi> and Lord-ships, &amp;c. The Apostle speaks of some, that <hi>will be rich,</hi> that set up their resolution they will be rich any wayes, by right or wrong, &amp;c. As these two vices, of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality</hi> and <hi>Covetousness</hi> are directly contrary; so I know-
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97861:9"/> no third <hi>ground</hi> of borrowing between them, except of <hi>necessity:</hi> Some have talked of <hi>lending</hi> upon <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> (and so of <hi>borrowing</hi>) to get to exercise their <hi>charity;</hi> by being better able to give to the poor or lend to the <hi>Needy</hi> freely: but they either forget, or misconstrue that <hi>Proverb</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <q>[He that gathtereth riches; by Ʋsury and increase; shall gather for him that will be merciful to the poor; <hi>Pro. 28.8.</hi>]</q> He himself may <hi>pretend</hi> such a thing, but hardly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>intended</hi> it, yet by the just <hi>providence</hi> of God, it shall at last fall into such a mans hands, as shall be <hi>mercifull</hi> to the poore. And yet if <hi>Ʋsury</hi> were lawfull, this were a probable, and speedy way to be <hi>charitable.</hi> A man of a great Estate, that had 1006 <hi>li.</hi> to spare to lend upon <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> might be able to give more in a yeer to relieve the <hi>poor,</hi> than most <hi>Ʋ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers,</hi> or <hi>rich</hi> men do in many. But I never heard an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this <hi>way,</hi> and end of lending. Though perhaps, some might strain the words of our Saviour to such a sence: <q>[Thou shouldst have put thy money to the exchanger that I might receive my own with <hi>Usury</hi>]</q> But I let that passe: the <hi>hinge</hi> of the question will hang upon this, the <hi>lawfulnesse</hi> to borrow out of <hi>Covetousnesse;</hi> to get wealth, as shall appear, when we have considered the other kind of <hi>Necessity:</hi> which is</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Real,</hi> cast upon a man, by some accident,<note place="margin">2. True &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, which is</note> and by the <hi>providence</hi> of God; and his gain, may be distinguished into <hi>imminent,</hi> or <hi>permanent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Imminent,</hi> or <hi>Occasional,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Imminent or occasional.</note> present necessity (for I want words to express this distinction) which arises from some sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>exigent:</hi> and this sometimes is incident to the <hi>Rich,</hi> and wealthy. As in the <hi>parable</hi> of the man, that had a friend come to him in the night: he having no bread nor provision at home, runnes to his neighbour, to <hi>borrow</hi> three loaves, till next day, when he would returne them againe with thanks: so in many the like cases, a man otherwise <hi>rich,</hi> may have a <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity</hi> cast upon him, to borrow some <hi>necessaries,</hi> even for his life: or <hi>money,</hi> (being in a strange place, &amp; his own spent) to carry him home, &amp;c. But then, the thing is so <hi>small,</hi> or the time so <hi>short,</hi> that it may well go for a <hi>courtesie,</hi> scarcely valuable, but with the like another time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Permanent,</hi> or <hi>continual,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Permanent or (like to be) perpetual.</note> at least likely to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out supply, <hi>heavy</hi> upon the borrower; by reason of his poor
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97861:10"/> and weake estate. And this is the case of <hi>poor</hi> men only: &amp; to bend to such, is an act of <hi>charity,</hi> as to the former, an act of <hi>Courtesie,</hi> which is a larger <hi>charity.</hi> The question then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, is not to be meant of this <hi>latter</hi> sort of <hi>Borrowers,</hi> whom in all reason, we must allow to borrow, in their <hi>neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity:</hi> but of the former kind, which is sometimes <hi>feigned,</hi> for the most part <hi>forced,</hi> by their owne lusts of <hi>Prodigality,</hi> and <hi>Covetousnesse,</hi> and especially of this latter, that borrows meerly to <hi>encrease their wealth:</hi> which shall be manifested, when we have premised a third thing.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. what is meant by bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease wealth</note>3. What we mean, by borrowing to increase his wealth (to prevent exceptions) for it may be said; you allow a <hi>Needy</hi> Trades-man to borrow, and that <hi>freely:</hi> but he may borrow to increase his (little) estate: which contradicts your <hi>Problemes.</hi> To which I answer; 1. It cannot proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be said, such a man borrows to <hi>increase</hi> his wealth; for that supposes him to have <hi>wealth</hi> already: but he borrows onely to be able to <hi>manage</hi> his Trade, that by getting some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by the <hi>use</hi> and imployment of the money borrowed, he may not <hi>need</hi> to borrow heareafter. 2. I mean it therefore of such a <hi>borrower,</hi> as hath an <hi>abundant,</hi> at least a <hi>competent</hi> estate already, which he is allowed to <hi>improve</hi> to the utmost, in all lawful ways, as his <hi>entrusted Talent:</hi> but not to <hi>borrow,</hi> meerly to <hi>advance</hi> his estate, no not if he can borrow <hi>freely,</hi> much less upon <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> when he hath no true, real, just, <hi>need</hi> to borrow. Having thus illustrated the <hi>Problem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Problem proved.</note> I come now to indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the <hi>proof</hi> thereof, in manner following.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. Its natural principle.</note>1. This seems a <hi>natural notion,</hi> common to all that go to <hi>bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row;</hi> they still pretend <hi>necessity,</hi> true or false, feigned or real; or they would not borrow: I lack this or that; I have great <hi>need,</hi> I pray, lend me this or that, or so much money. And indeed <hi>borrowing</hi> is so great a trouble, that it is grown into a proverb, <q>
                  <hi>[He that goes a borrowing, goes a sorrowing.]</hi>
               </q> So that he were scarcely <hi>wise,</hi> that would borrow, were he not forced to it, by <hi>Necessity.</hi> Hence was that Law, or <hi>Aphorisme</hi> of <hi>Plato,</hi> written (it seems) by the <hi>candle-light</hi> of nature; <q>[No man ought to borrow water of his neigbours well till he, hath drawn his own dry to the bottome;]</q>
               <hi>which holds as wel, in all</hi> commodities <hi>else, of which the life of man hath need.</hi> A great <hi>Patron</hi> of <hi>Ʋsury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Solmas.</note> approves of this <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Plato,</hi> but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97861:10"/> restrains it too strictly, t <hi>poor</hi> men onely. <hi>As</hi> if <hi>rich</hi> men might borrow, before they are come to the <hi>bottom</hi> of their estates, that is, before they <hi>need;</hi> but poor men might not: which seems very unreasonable. Yea, in <hi>reason,</hi> poor men should rather have this liberty, than the rich, though <hi>Plato</hi> allows it to neither. <hi>Plutarch</hi> also (by the same <hi>twilight</hi>) dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned this truth: He blamed them both, the rich and poore, for borrowing (upon Usury) when thus he argued; <q>[If thou beest very poor; why dost thou borrow that, which thou canst not restore? if rich, why dost borrow, when thou hast of thine owne, and needst not borrow?]</q> So that <hi>Nature</hi> it selfe, taught them what I affirme. And if we look back, to the <hi>beginning</hi> of nature; In <hi>innocency,</hi> as there would have been no <hi>want,</hi> so no <hi>need</hi> of borrowing. After the <hi>Fall,</hi> the first kind of <hi>borrowing</hi> was in case of <hi>necessity</hi> onely. No man had all, none but wanted something, which another had: hence it came, that they were forced, either to <hi>exchange</hi> one thing for another, or to <hi>borrow</hi> one of another; and the requital was the <hi>lending again,</hi> at another time, what they had need to borrow.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>principles</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> that is, the <hi>Scriptures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Its a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> do many wayes confirme, what I assert <q>[that no man ought to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, but the needy, that is, meerely to inrich himselfe.]</q> this is thus made good.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Expressely;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Expressely.</note> the <hi>Scripture</hi> forbids running into debt, and continuing in debt, without just cause, as <q>[<hi>Rom. 13.8.</hi> owe nothing to any man, but to love one another.]</q> which to me seemes to require, that all <hi>civil debts,</hi> be either wisely <hi>prevented,</hi> or speedily <hi>discharged:</hi> that is, that if men be out of debt, they be careful, not to come into debt: and if they be in debt, they should hasten out; unlesse <hi>urgent</hi> necessity force them thereunto: either to goe into debt, or to stay in debt, if able to pay it: which is the onely dispensation from this precept: but now I assume, they that <hi>borrow</hi> to <hi>inrich themselves,</hi> when they need not, run themselves into <hi>debt,</hi> without any just <hi>necessity,</hi> continue voluntarily in debt, when able to pay it, and so sin against this precept.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>Consequence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. By Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</note> they forbid it often, when they forbid the very <hi>desire</hi> to be rich, much more rich indeavours to saits<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie those desires.<note place="margin">1. From the contrary a wayes.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. From the contrary; and that two wayes. 1. The
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97861:11"/> Scriptures, the word of God, require <hi>Contentment,</hi> with our present estate; <q>[<hi>1 Tim. 6.9.</hi> If we have food and rayment (convenient for our condition) let us be therewith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. <hi>Heb. 13.5.</hi> Let your conversation be without covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and be content with such things, as you have.]</q> The argument is thus framed; If we be commanded to be <hi>contented with necessaries,</hi> then they that desire, and seek after <hi>Superfluities</hi> (as riches are) do sin: but the first is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently true: ergo. Again, <hi>Covetousness</hi> is a sinne, often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry'd in Scripture: but not to be <hi>content</hi> with our estate, is a fruit and hath a tang of <hi>Covetousnesse:</hi> for the <hi>Apostle</hi> would have men to be content, lest they be concluded to be <hi>covetous;</hi>
               <q>[Whence it follows (saith <hi>Estius</hi>) that he, that is not contented with such things as he hath, but desires and seekes to bee richer (for he is supposed to be rich already; or not to be needie) is guilty of Covetousnesse.]</q> 2. What we may not <hi>pray</hi> for, that we may not <hi>desire,</hi> or seek after: but it is not lawful to pray for <hi>Superfluities:</hi> witness our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, who teaches us to pray only for our <hi>daily bread,</hi> that is, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for <hi>necessaries,</hi> So <q>[<hi>Pro. 30.8, 9.</hi> Feed me with food con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for mee:]</q> Nay so far is he from praying for riches, that he deprecates riches, as well as poverty, <q>[Give me nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther riches nor poverty:]</q> for reasons there given, and made use of, by and by.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. From the causes of it. 1. Discontent.</note>2. From the <hi>causes,</hi> that set men on borrowing, to this end, <hi>to be rich:</hi> and they are one of these; 1. <hi>Discontentednesse</hi> with their condition: this is intimated in the former Scriptures, that require <hi>Contentment.</hi> Men are not contented to be men of <hi>meane rank;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1. By desire to be rich.</note> but they will be rich, that they may be <hi>honoured,</hi> that they may live in <hi>pleasures,</hi> and worldly delights, which their present estate will not procure them. 2. <hi>Covetousness,</hi> which is discovered, 1. by the <hi>will</hi> to be rich. 1 Tim. 6.9. called the <hi>love of money;</hi> the root of all evill; even of <hi>prodiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> it self; sometimes the same man that is <hi>prodigall,</hi> may be covetous also he covets to have abundance, which he may <hi>prodigally</hi> spend upon his lusts: he spares where he should spend, that he may spend, where he should spare. 2. By <hi>Hasting</hi> to be rich,<note place="margin">2. By hasting to be rich.</note>
               <q>[<hi>Prov. 23.4.</hi> Labour not to be rich: cease from thine own Wisdom.]</q> These think themselves to be <hi>Wise</hi> men; and if they had but money, they could easily, and speedily be rich: this puts them upon borrowing, what they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97861:11"/> want, to get, what they so earnestly desire; So <q>[<hi>Prov. 28.22.</hi> He that hath an evill eye, hasteth to be rich; or he that hasteth to be rich hath an evill eye.]</q> that is, a <hi>covetous</hi> eye, which is called, the <hi>lust of the eyes:</hi> for a man may commit, or act <hi>covetousness</hi> (as well as <hi>adultery</hi>) with his eye: <hi>But what follows in the place?</hi>
               <q>[He considereth not, that poverty shall come upon him.]</q> God commonly <hi>crossing,</hi> if not <hi>cursing</hi> such <hi>Covetous</hi> (indeed <hi>Idolatrous</hi>) desires, of such as set up <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> for their God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From the <hi>Ends</hi> of such unnecessary Borrowing:<note place="margin">3. From the ends of such unnecessary Borrowing.</note> which are specified above, to be one of these two. 1. <hi>Prodigality</hi> to spend upon their lusts, of severall kinds; <hi>Pride, Vain-glory, Riot, Gaming, &amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>Covetousnesse</hi> to advance an Estate, to make themselves and their posterity great, by great Trading, Purchasing, &amp;c. To borrow to spend it <hi>prodigally,</hi> will not be defended (I think) by any Patron: The other of growing great, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is <hi>clothed</hi> with better garments, cloaked by other names of good <hi>Husbandry, Diligence, Activenesse</hi> in a call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. Some men, (they say) have more <hi>nimble fancies,</hi> more <hi>Active Spirits,</hi> more able to manage a bigger <hi>stock,</hi> to drive a greater trade, to improve five <hi>Talents</hi> better, than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers can two. But what are their <hi>ends</hi> and intentions? are they not to grow rich <hi>hastily?</hi> and that with <hi>undermining,</hi> if not the <hi>undoing</hi> of others, of their own profession: Yea, of other <hi>professions</hi> also sometimes, by dealing in, and medling with more <hi>callings</hi> than one.</p>
            <p n="4">4. From the many <hi>evill effects,</hi> and mischiefes,<note place="margin">4. From the evil effects.</note> that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon such <hi>unnecessary</hi> Borrowing, for this end to become <hi>Rich:</hi> whereof these are some:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Upon <hi>Himself,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Upon himself.</note> in his own personal condition: and they these two: 1. A <hi>Curse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. A Curse.</note> by borrowing when he needs not; It is so threatned, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28 44. to <hi>borrow,</hi> as contrarily, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised as a <hi>Blessing,</hi> to be able to lend. If any shall say (as some do say) To borrow for <hi>need,</hi> is indeed a curse, but not to borrow when he hath no need: I answer (besides that this beggs the question now before us, that it is lawful to borrow without any need) it seemes strange to me, that a man should be able, by his <hi>own Wit</hi> and Wisdom, to turn a <hi>Curse</hi> into a Blessing: or rather turn a <hi>Blessing</hi> into a Curse: that is, that when he needs not borrow, but is able to lend, which is a Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97861:12"/> he should run himself into a Curse (as the consequent <hi>mischiefs</hi> will evince) to borrow when he needeth not. 2. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>mischief</hi> is,<note place="margin">2. Slavery.</note> that being <hi>free,</hi> by borrowing when he needs not, he runs himself into <hi>Slavery:</hi> which is a misery suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, as <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Freedom</hi> is a special mercy: and we ought to stand fast, in the Libertie, which God hath given us; (as the Apostle in another case.) Now <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <q>[Prov. 22.7. <hi>The borrower is servant to the lender.</hi>]</q> He is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed his <hi>slave,</hi> whom he keeps in <hi>bonds,</hi> and fetters of <hi>bills</hi> and <hi>obligations,</hi> &amp;c. and upon all occasions, though he be his far <hi>Inferiour,</hi> is ready to <hi>Lord</hi> it over him, and for non-paiment, at his day,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cartwright</hi> in locum.</note> to lay him up in prison. So that (as one sayes) <q>[Such a man hath so many cruel Lords and Masters, as he hath Creditors: And this may teach us (saith he) not hastily to cast our selves into debt, though we need much more, if we need not.]</q> 3. To run voluntarily into debt, when there is no need, fills the head and heart with <hi>cares,</hi> or <hi>scares,</hi> or <hi>griefs,</hi> and many perplexities; which as <hi>th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnes,</hi> do prick and torment the soul. <q>[1 Tim. 6.9, 10. <hi>They that will be rich, fall into snares, and pierce themselves thorow with many sorrowes.</hi>]</q> And were not he a mad man, that when he might lie upon a <hi>Down-bed,</hi> would willingly cast himself into a <hi>thicket</hi> of thornes to sleep upon? <hi>Debt</hi> (at least to an honest man) breaks his <hi>sleep,</hi> distasts his <hi>food,</hi> distempers his <hi>heart</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Upon his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state and poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note>2. But he proves as injurious, to his <hi>estate</hi> and posterity: It's observable, what the <hi>wisest</hi> of men saies, <q>[Prov. 20.21. <hi>An inheritance may be gotten hastily at the first, but the end thereof shall not be blessed.</hi>]</q> Those great <hi>Dealers,</hi> &amp; borrowers in the wo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld; either they <hi>thrive</hi> not at all, God crossing them for their <hi>Discontent,</hi> and worldly mindednesse; or if they do, yet either they live, to see it all <hi>wasted;</hi> or in a generation or two, the world may see it all <hi>dispersed;</hi> and their posterity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced again to their <hi>Parents</hi> first condition, and well if not to a worse.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Upon his owne soul ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing it.</note>3. The worst of alls, that such Borrowers, are too often injurious to their own souls, exposing themselves needlesly both to temptations and sins. 1. To temptations;<note place="margin">1. To tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> so the Apostle expresly, <q>[<hi>1 Tim. 6.9.</hi> They that will be rich, fall into temptation:]</q> and that two ways, first, <hi>passively</hi> to be tempted by riches; either get to them ill, or spend them ill,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97861:12"/> or keep them ill: which is to cross their daily prayer, <hi>[lead us not into temptation;]</hi> and these lead themselves into tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation. Secondly, <hi>actively</hi> by tempting God, having no permission of such desires; and endeavours to be rich, nor promise of a blessing: This is to tempt and try God, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will prosper such endeavours or no: Suppose he do succeed them, yet having no promise, there can be no solid comfort in them: If he crosses them in these undertakings, (as oft he does) how are they exposed to other temptations, to use shifts and frauds, to deceive their Creditors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. To many sins.</note> But 2. They expose themselves to many sins; <q>[They that will be rich, fall into a snare also, and into many foolish and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful lusts, which drown'd men in destruction, and perdition.]</q> In general, the same <hi>Wise</hi> man tels us, <q>[He that maketh haste to be rich, shall not be innocent, <hi>Prov. 28.20.</hi>]</q> This is illustrated by the contrary, <q>[A faithful man shall abound with blessings.]</q>
               <hi>A faithful man</hi> (whether he mean one, that hath <hi>faith</hi> to trust God, which is opposed to making <hi>haste</hi> to be rich, as the Prophet, [<hi>He that believeth, maketh not haste,</hi> Isa. 28, 16.] or a man of <hi>faithfulnesses,</hi> as the Original hath it; one that is <hi>true</hi> in his words, and <hi>plain, just,</hi> faithful in his dealings; which way, the world thinks, either none, or about, and too long, to get riches) such a man going <hi>slowly,</hi> shall <hi>abound with blessings:</hi> intimating, that a man that makes <hi>haste</hi> to be rich, (as such <hi>Borrowers</hi> do) is a man that <q>[trusts not on the Lord, but leans on his own wisdom, <hi>Prov. 3.5.</hi>]</q> and is too often, <hi>false</hi> in his words and promises, and <hi>fraudulent</hi> in his deeds; subject to <hi>lying,</hi> defrauding, oppression, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are (as he thinks) the <hi>shortest,</hi> and neerest way to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his <hi>hasty</hi> desires to be rich: but more often prove the <hi>furthest</hi> way about, and expose him to the <hi>curses</hi> of God. And upon this consideration, it is observed by one:<note place="margin">Salmas.</note> That the <hi>Persians</hi> of old, did utterly dislike borrowing (upon Usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) because <hi>Borrowers</hi> are very prone to <hi>lie,</hi> deceive and be <hi>unthankful:</hi> In a word, <hi>Hasty desires,</hi> and endeavours to be rich (whereof great <hi>borrowing</hi> without need, is a <hi>Symptom,</hi> exposes a man to sins of all kinds of <hi>Omission,</hi> multitude of businesses causing him to neglect holy <hi>services</hi> in private or publick, and of <hi>Commission;</hi> as lying, <hi>fraud,</hi> oppression) pride, and noysome lusts: Therefore <hi>Agur</hi> deprecated Riches,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97861:13"/>
               <q>[<hi>Give me not riches, lest I be full and deny thee,</hi> &amp;c. Pro. 30.9.]</q> These at present eat out the <hi>heart</hi> and vitals of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the power of Godliness, and at last, drown too many in <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> and destruction, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. Riches, at which they aim, are well compared to <hi>thornes,</hi> not onely because they <hi>pierce</hi> the soul, with <hi>cares, fears, &amp;c.</hi> but also because they <hi>choak</hi> the Word, and make it unfruitful. Mark your great <hi>Dealers</hi> in the world, either they have no <hi>Religion,</hi> or if any, it is <hi>eaten up</hi> and withered, by worldly-mindedness: that therefore which is the root that bears such <hi>gall</hi> and <hi>worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> cannot be good.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We may argue <hi>à pari,</hi> from the like: It is not lawful to <hi>beg</hi> without urgent,<note place="margin">5. <hi>A pari</hi> from the like.</note>
               <hi>real necessity,</hi> therefore nor to <hi>borrow:</hi> The reason is, because they are both alike <hi>objects</hi> of <hi>charity;</hi> allowed only in cases of such <hi>necessity.</hi> As then it is unlawful for a <hi>rich</hi> man, that needs not, to <hi>beg;</hi> so for a man that <hi>needs</hi> not, to borrow. <hi>Borrowing</hi> and <hi>begging,</hi> (and so lending and giving) are commonly joyn'd together in Scripture; <q>[<hi>Deut. 15.8, 9 Mat. 5.42.</hi> Give to him that asketh, and from him that would borrow of thee, turn not thou away.]</q> Hence it was observed afore, that the texts which speak of borrowing (and forbid Usury) <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.25. <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.37. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <hi>lending,</hi> only to <hi>needy</hi> borrowers: <q>[My people, that is poor; waxen poor, whose hand shakes, that borrows victuals.]</q> The argument from all this, shall close up this discourse, when an objection is removed, which is this; <hi>Ʋsury</hi> in all the texts, (in your own assertion and confession) is prohibited to be taken only of the <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>needy;</hi> and consequently <hi>lawful</hi> of the rich; and then the rich may <hi>borrow,</hi> that need not: I answer, 1. By denying the consequence; by a like <hi>inference;</hi> Oppression is forbidden towards the poor and stranger, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.21. will it follow hence, that its lawful to <hi>oppress</hi> the rich, or a neighbour? 2. All <hi>Ʋsury</hi> being <hi>Nesher,</hi> biting and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressive, it is here intended to be forbidden to the rich, though chiefly to the <hi>poor,</hi> who most need to borrow. 3. If a <hi>rich</hi> man fall (as he may) into a present <hi>urgent need,</hi> he also falls under the <hi>Law,</hi> as at this time, and in this case, a needy man, and so is by me <hi>allowed</hi> to borrow, but still <hi>freely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> A Testimonio</note>6. Lastly, we dispute <hi>à Testimonio,</hi> the assertions of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones</hi> of Usury; hear how, neer they come, to affirme our <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97861:13"/> That <hi>necessity</hi> is the only true ground of borrowing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Salmasius</hi> himself, the greatest and strongest <hi>Advocate</hi> for <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> saith thus, <q>[In <hi>Judaea,</hi> where was neither Merchandize, nor Money, nor was there any great Wealth or Ryot, by means thereof, only poor men did need to borrow: but that they should be oppressed, especially of their own brethren, seemed hard to the Law-giver.]</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Author of a <hi>Tract,</hi> called <hi>Quaest. Quodlibetica, &amp;c.</hi> pag. 8. <q>[<hi>The borrowing of such Indigent persons, as are spoken of in the Law, being of things of so small value (that the use of them for a small season, was scarcely valuable) might be a great reason, of the prohibition of</hi> Usury.]</q> And pag. 28. <q>[<hi>I acknowledge (saith he) the word</hi> Nesher, <hi>might well denote some malignant quality in Ʋsury, because the first kind of borrowing in the world, was in case only of necessity: and to ask an overplus in such a case, was a sin, that well deserved the worst name.</hi>]</q> And yet, both <hi>Salma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius,</hi> and <hi>himself,</hi> do plead strongly, that <hi>Ʋsury</hi> now is lawfully taken of the <hi>poor;</hi> if at least, we relieve him some other way: which I leave to the Readers consideration: And propound the Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <q>[If none but the really needie (as afore explained) may borrow, and when they borrow must be lent unto, freely; then all Ʋsury is unlawful:]</q> The <hi>Antecedent</hi> is proved above, in both the <hi>parts</hi> of it, from the three <hi>Original Texts,</hi> &amp; from light of nature, and <hi>Scripture</hi> reason. The <hi>Consequence,</hi> is thus made good; If <hi>wealthy</hi> men, that <hi>need</hi> not, may not borrow at all, either to spend it <hi>prodigally,</hi> or to use it <hi>covetously;</hi> to increase their <hi>wealth,</hi> then none may lend to such; and consequently not upon Usury; and so all <hi>Ʋsury</hi> is unlawful, taken of rich or poor. This <hi>Consequence,</hi> that none may lawfully lend to such, is my fift <hi>Theorem,</hi> which waits its time of further confirmation.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Some ANIMADVERSIONS upon the Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the Case of <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> by a Reverend and very Learned Dr. <hi>D. H. Decad.</hi> 1. <hi>Case</hi> 1. <hi>"Whether it be lawfull, to raise any profit, by the loan of Money?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving given forth the former <hi>Essay,</hi> upon the main questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which if it be strongly <hi>bottomed,</hi> may of it selfe, put an end to the present <hi>Controversie:</hi> yet it shall not be amisse, to manifest the <hi>strength,</hi> or weakness, of some of the Arguments, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97861:14"/> distinctions, brought by some very learned men, for the <hi>Allowance</hi> of some kind of <hi>Ʋsury:</hi> And amongst many <hi>Patrons</hi> thereof, I have made choice of one, who, as he appears <hi>latest</hi> in publique, and so may be thought, to bring the <hi>strength</hi> of all the former: So he was well known, to be a man, of no lesse <hi>piety,</hi> than <hi>learning;</hi> and by his <hi>Age,</hi> and <hi>Gravity</hi> believed to be of a <hi>Mature</hi> and Solid Judgement; fit to make a <hi>Casuist,</hi> on whole <hi>Resolutions</hi> of Cases in matters of <hi>Conscience,</hi> men that were <hi>Scrupulous,</hi> might more safely rest and rely. Upon which considerations, I was very <hi>eager</hi> to read his <hi>Determination</hi> upon the Case in hand; here (if any where) expecting that <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> which (under favour be it spok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en) upon search I have not found; but by want thereof, am rather confirmed in my own <hi>opinion,</hi> as I fear, others are in their <hi>practice</hi> of Usury: Some things I shall say in general, to his Resolution; 1. That I find not in it, any <hi>Definition</hi> of Usury (wherein others also are defective) which had it been done, it might have been more <hi>easie,</hi> both for him to <hi>Resolve</hi> the Case, and for others to <hi>judge</hi> of his Resolution. 2. That he is <hi>inconstant,</hi> in his assertions, and sometimes <hi>contradictorius</hi> to himself, implicitely, if not expressely and directly. 3. That yet this must be said for the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>Rev: Doctor,</hi> that he, though he seem to allow, in some cases, <hi>profit,</hi> for the <hi>loane</hi> of money, yet makes <hi>all Ʋsury,</hi> properly so called, especially taken of the <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>needy,</hi> to be unlawfull: whereas some of late, make all to be <hi>lawful,</hi> taken of poor or rich.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>Decision</hi> of the question, he proceeds warily, by <hi>distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of circumstances, (which some others have altogether negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) before he make his determination of the <hi>Case,</hi> as thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>[First, Who it is that borrows? A poor neighbour that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained out of need: or a Merchant, that takes up money for a free Trade, for the inriching of himselfe: or a rich man, that lays it out upon superfluous occasions. From the first, you must not expect any profit, for the loane: but for the other, the case is different. For God hath not commanded you, to love any man more than your self: and there can be no reason, why you should vaile your own just advantage, to another mans excess.]</q> Where 1. It is observable, that the Doctor hath made a right and full <hi>enumeration</hi> of Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers. 1. Poor and needy. 2. Such as borrow to <hi>inrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,</hi> the rich <hi>Merchant,</hi> (that is, the <hi>covetous.</hi>) 3. <hi>Prod<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gals</hi> that borrow to spend it on their excessive <hi>lusts,</hi> and superfluities. 2. But herein he yeelds, I think, too much, that the <hi>Merchant</hi> borrowing to <hi>inrich</hi> himself, or the <hi>prodigal</hi> to spend it on <hi>super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97861:14"/> may <hi>borrow,</hi> and be <hi>lent</hi> unto; who have (I yet believe) no <hi>right</hi> to borrow, nor can be <hi>lent</hi> unto, without being <hi>accessary</hi> to their sins. The latter, <q>[To lend to a <hi>prodigall,</hi> to promote his wanton lusts, and superfluous expences]</q>
                  <hi>is by all sober men grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be sinfull.</hi> The former is as truly <hi>sinfull,</hi> though not so ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily granted, or proved to be such: Yet to borrow (for no <hi>need</hi>) meerly to <hi>inrich</hi> himself, seems to be a <hi>sprig</hi> of that root of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, <hi>Covetousnesse,</hi> so much decryed in Scripture; which if it be sinfull in the <hi>Borrower,</hi> cannot but be so in the <hi>Lender,</hi> who wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that cursed <hi>root</hi> by lending his money: Now if these two sorts may not borrow, it remains to assert, that none but the <hi>Needy,</hi> may borrow, or be lent unto; and then no <hi>profit</hi> for the <hi>loane</hi> of money, being lawful to be taken of him, all <hi>Ʋsury</hi> for lending, is unlawful. 3. His reasons are in themselves good and true, but if applyed to the case, they <hi>beg</hi> the question; That it is lawful to <hi>lend,</hi> to such, or for such, as the two last sorts, to <hi>borrow.</hi> True it is, God hath not commanded men to love another better than themselves; nor yet to vail their own advantage to anothers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess: But suppose the <hi>Merchant</hi> borrow, not to use it to excesse, but to get gain, to inrich himself, and to satisfie his <hi>lust of the eyes</hi> which is covetousness; the question is, whether such may borrow, which this reason supposes to be granted. On the other side, I am not to vail my own just advantage to anothers excess; but suppose I cannot use it at my own advantage (the <hi>Patrons</hi> of Usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, allow only such to lend upon Usury, Orphans, Widows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is it lawfull then to lend it upon Usury, to such as will use it to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess? this is taken for granted also. In a word, suppose I can improve it (which the Dr. <hi>supposes</hi> I can) is it <hi>necessary</hi> for me, or lawful, to lend it to one that is <hi>prodigall,</hi> that will use it to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess? If not, then I ought not to lend it to another, that will so use it: If so, then I say again, he <hi>begs</hi> the question; for I ought to use, and improve it my self, and not to lend it to one that will so abuse it, to excesse; nor (I think) to one that <hi>needs</hi> it not, but to <hi>increase</hi> his own wealth. 4. I think, there is no <hi>Ʋsurer,</hi> but will go away satisfied with these grants from the pen of so <hi>grave, learned, pious a Divine:</hi> and think himself wise enough now, to <hi>justifie</hi> the worst of his <hi>Ʋsury.</hi> For as he will think no man <hi>poor,</hi> that is able to give him good <hi>security</hi> for his money: So he is willing, and desirous to deal with none, but <q>[the rich Merchant, that takes up money for a free Trade, for the inriching of himselfe, or the prodigall person, that layes it out upon excess, and superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97861:15"/> occasions]</q>
                  <hi>from whom the Dr. more than seems, for good reasons, to allow him Usury, yet not without some other</hi> Cautions.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>[<hi>Secondly,</hi> Ʋpon what termes do you lend? Ʋpon an absolute compact, for certain increase (what ever become of the principall) or upon a friendly trust to a voluntary satisfaction, according to the improvement of the money? The former is not safe, if benefit be disappointed, and rigorously to require profit in that case, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest oppression: The other is lawfull, being nothing but gratitude, which with the conscionable, is a bond no lesse strong, than that of law, and justice.]</q> To which, it may be returned, 1. The <hi>compact,</hi> is a part of the <hi>Definition</hi> of Usury, <hi>Lucrum ex mutuo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum:</hi> So that if there be no <hi>compact,</hi> express or implicite, it is not <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> which cannot be required, (nor need to be paid) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>compact:</hi> and it is <hi>absolute,</hi> among <hi>Ʋsurers,</hi> what ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the <hi>principall.</hi> 2. <hi>Gratitude</hi> is one thing, <hi>Ʋsury</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Even the poorest borrower, <hi>gain</hi> or gain not, is bound to be <hi>thankefull,</hi> yet to take <hi>profit</hi> of him, for the <hi>loane</hi> of money, is already judged to be unlawful. 3. This also supposes, what is <hi>denyed,</hi> that it is lawfull for such as borrow for no <hi>need,</hi> but to the <hi>ill ends</hi> afore, to borrow, and to be <hi>lent</hi> unto. 4. We shall finde hereafter, that the Dr. allows an <hi>absolute compact,</hi> of certain gain, in some cases, and so, I think, differs from himselfe. But I go on.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>[<hi>Thirdly,</hi> If upon an absolute compact, is it upon a certainty, or an adventure? for where you are willing to hazard the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, there can be no reason, but you should take part of the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.]</q> But besides that I understand not, how an <hi>absolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact,</hi> can be upon an <hi>Adventure;</hi> this varies the question, from <hi>loan</hi> or lending, or <hi>partnership,</hi> and so is not to the case of <hi>Ʋsury:</hi> for in <hi>partnership</hi> a man must be content to bear a part in the <hi>losse,</hi> as well as in the <hi>advantage:</hi> and if a man resolve to do so, there is no reason but he should take <hi>part</hi> of the profit.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>[<hi>Fourthly,</hi> Where the Trade is ordinarily certain, there are yet further considerations to be had. <hi>1.</hi> That the value of money is arbitrable, in severall places. <hi>2.</hi> What ever is saleable, is capable of profit, in the loan of it, as an horse or an oxe may be let. <hi>3.</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is not only the price of other commodities, but it selfe in some ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses is a traffiqueable commodity; the price whereof rises and falls, in severall Countreys, and mony thus considered, may be bought &amp; sold, and improved to a just profit.]</q> To which it may briefly be said; 1. Where money is a <hi>traffiqueable</hi> commodity, yet there is cōmonly a <hi>State-prohibition,</hi> to transport money to a place where
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97861:15"/> it is dearer prized, and so it's unlawful to raise any <hi>profit</hi> by it, that way. 2. From the 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg> consideration, we may reasonably conclude against <hi>lending</hi> of <hi>money</hi> upon Usury: Whatsoever commodity is not <hi>saleable,</hi> is not <hi>capable</hi> of profit, in the <hi>loan</hi> of it: But <hi>money,</hi> as it is the price of other commodities, is not <hi>saleable.</hi> Ergo. The instances by him given, of an <hi>horse,</hi> or <hi>oxe,</hi> are <hi>heterogeneous;</hi> for they are capable of more contracts, <hi>lending, letting, selling,</hi> as things, not spent in the use; but <hi>money,</hi> being only the price of other commodities, is spent in the use, and so cannot, or should not be <hi>sold,</hi> or <hi>let:</hi> At least, that's the question, of which in the next: but I adde, 3. If money as <hi>Merchandize,</hi> may be <hi>bought</hi> and <hi>sold,</hi> that's nothing to the <hi>Case</hi> in hand; which is in <hi>lending;</hi> where not the <hi>money</hi> it selfe, but the use of the money (if any thing) is sold, and bought. To which he speaks in the next.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>[The main doubt is, whether money meerly considered, as the price of all other commodities, may be let forth to profit, and a warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table increase: For the resolving whereof, be it determined, That all Ʋsury, which is an absolute contract, for the meer loan of money, is unlawful, by all kind of laws, both divine, and humane.]</q> This alone were a full <hi>Resolution</hi> of the Case, and utterly destroys the <hi>Ʋsurers</hi> Trade; for as he lends his <hi>money,</hi> meerly as the price of other things (not as a <hi>Merchandize</hi> improveable elswhere) so, his <hi>contract</hi> is absolute, for the <hi>meer loan</hi> of money, (whatever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the principal) and for nothing else in him the <hi>Lender;</hi> whether the <hi>Borrower</hi> be rich or poor, gain or lose: His Reasons are very considerable to this purpose, and weighty. <q>[<hi>1.</hi> Nature teaches us, that metals are not a thing capable of superfetation. <hi>2.</hi> that no man ought to set a price, on that which is none of his own Time. <hi>3.</hi> That the use of the stock, once received is not the Lenders, but the Borrowers: the power and right of disposing the principal, is, by contract, transferred to him that receives it. So that he that takes the Interest, by vertue of such transaction, doth but in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly, and legal fashion, rob the Borrower.]</q> This witness is full, and the reasons strong, against <hi>all Ʋsury</hi> whatever, of any persons whatever, rich or poor. For 1. <hi>mony</hi> does not <hi>breed</hi> mony, more to a <hi>rich</hi> man, than to a poor man. 2. <hi>Time</hi> cannot be prized, more to one, than to another. 3. The <hi>use</hi> of it, once received, is the Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, rich, as well as poor; the power and right of disposing the <hi>principal,</hi> being equally transferred to both. Let the conclusion then be added; He that takes Interest, by vertue of such <hi>transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> doth but in a mannerly and legal fashion, rob the Borrowers.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97861:16"/> How this is reconcileable with what was said in the first Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, I cannot imagine: or with that which now follows.</p>
               <p>Thus he saith, <q>[However it is unlawful to covenant for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain profit, for the meer loan of mony: yet there may be, and are circumstances appending to the loan, which may admit some benefit to the Lender, to be lawfully made, for the use of his mony, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially these two. <hi>1.</hi> The loss that he sustains, And <hi>2.</hi> the gain that he misses, by the want of the sum lent: for what reason, that to pleasure another man, I should hurt my self? that I should in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich another by my own loss?]</q> To which divers things may be said; for besides that this <hi>interferes,</hi> with the last recited asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and with those three Arguments, strong against all Usury; I add: 1. <hi>Lending</hi> being an act (not of <hi>justice,</hi> but) of <hi>charity,</hi> the Lender is not to respect his own <hi>loss</hi> or <hi>gain</hi> he might have made, but the good and <hi>profit</hi> of the Borrower, even sometimes with the loss of his principal: <q>
                     <hi>[lend looking for nothing again]</hi>
                  </q> 2. By this way, Usury is lawfully taken, of the <hi>poorest</hi> Borrower; for I may sustain loss, or miss some gain, I might have made for want of my money lent him. 3. It may also be lawful to <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> for gain, for the <hi>meer loan</hi> of the mony; for from the first day of lending my money, I may meet with some <hi>loss,</hi> or miss some <hi>gain,</hi> for want of my money: yea, supposing (as he does) that the Lender is one, that at the very time of <hi>lending,</hi> could improve it to his own <hi>advantage; Ʋsury,</hi> or (as he calls it) <hi>Interest</hi> may be ever lawful, and lawfully covenanted for; and that absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for so he saith, <q>[If there be a true danger of loss, to me immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, when the transaction is made, nothing hinders, but that I may by compact, make sure such a sum, as may be sufficient for my indemnity or gain, I for go, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> p. 10, 11. and more to the same purpose: Thus now, all <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> is nothing but <hi>Interest:</hi> whereas <hi>Interest</hi> had wont to be taken in this sense, when for <hi>delay,</hi> after the appointed day of payment, the <hi>Lender</hi> suffered loss, or missed gain (having lent it <hi>freely</hi>) but now, <hi>Interest,</hi> and so <hi>Ʋsury</hi> may be <hi>due</hi> from the very day of lending; when the Lender fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sees a danger of loss, or forgoes a present profit: and that <hi>Ʋsury</hi> may be covenanted for, with any Lender, poor or rich, though he perhaps, makes none or little <hi>gain</hi> of the money; yea, loses of the <hi>principal</hi> upon this Argument, <q>[What reason, that to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure another man, I should hurt my self?]</q> And what would any <hi>common Ʋsurer</hi> desire more? so that instead of <hi>confuting</hi> him, he hath <hi>confirm'd</hi> him more in his Practice and Trade. And this is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97861:16"/> the issue of all the <hi>distinctions,</hi> and <hi>cautions</hi> multiplied by the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons</hi> of Usury: nor can it be avoided, but in their way, (bringing the Case to the bar of <hi>corrupted Reason) Ʋsury</hi> may be just &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be taken of all, <hi>poor</hi> as well as rich; at least in some cases, if there were no <hi>divine Law</hi> against it: How to prevent this <hi>mischief,</hi> I find no way; but only what I have propounded, that if none but the <hi>needy</hi> may borrow, or be lent to, then, all <hi>Ʋsury</hi> for lending will prove <hi>unlawful:</hi> for when it is granted, (as it is by this learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr.) that rich and <hi>wealthy</hi> men, may borrow and be lent unto, (whether <hi>prodigal</hi> or <hi>covetous</hi>) there is a wide door opened for Usury: because of the reasons pleaded afore. 1. What reason is there, that to pleasure another, I should hurt my self? 2. That I should inrich another, by my own loss, when I could otherwise improve it? How to answer these, I know not; but by saying, In such a case, where the <hi>Borrower</hi> hath no <hi>need</hi> to borrow, but either to waste it <hi>prodigally,</hi> or to increase it <hi>covetously,</hi> and I can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it to my own advantage, I am not bouud to lend him my money, yea (I think) bound <hi>not to lend</hi> him; but <hi>charity</hi> bids me improve it my self; if I cannot improve it my self, yet I am <hi>bound</hi> not to lend it to such <hi>Borrowers,</hi> but to imploy it some other way, more safe and secure, without so many perplexities and scruples, as attend upon <hi>lending upon Ʋsury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the substance of his <hi>Resolution</hi> of the Case, there are some other things of lesser concernment observable. First he says, p. 13 <q>[Charitie will teach you, that every increase by loan of mony, is not Ʋsurary.]</q> But had he defined <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> he would have found, this teaching to be erroneous: For if <hi>Ʋsury</hi> be gain covenanted for lending of money, then <hi>gaine</hi> or increase for lending of money is <hi>Ʋsurary:</hi> the definition and the thing defined being convertible, as he well knew. And Usury thus defined, is rationally condemned by himself, by three strong Arguments.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Saith he, <q>[If you can find out a way by loan or sale, to advance your stock,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 6.</note> that may be free from all oppression and extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and beneficial as well to others, as your self; you need not fear to walk in it, with all honest security.]</q> In answer to this, I shall say, 1. In way of <hi>sale,</hi> it may be possible to find out such a way; but in way of <hi>loan</hi> of money, it will be very hard, if not impossible, to meet with such a way, as is free from all <hi>oppression;</hi> if either his <hi>Assertion,</hi> or his <hi>Arguments</hi> be of any strength: unless by <hi>lending</hi> freely, to the <hi>needie</hi> only, which may expect a blessing from God: which only makes a man <hi>innocently,</hi> and <hi>comfortably</hi> rich: And
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97861:17"/> therefore there can be little <hi>security,</hi> in walking in such a way, especially there being so many <hi>scruples</hi> to be answered, and so many <hi>cautions</hi> to be observed, &amp; as he saith, <q>[our hearts being too apt to beguile us, in misapplications; and rather to draw the Rule to us, than our selves to the Rule.]</q> Better therefore it were, and safer, to improve their <hi>stocks,</hi> any other lawful way, (as he sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses they can) than to lend to such as <hi>need</hi> not, to entangle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, with so many <hi>scruples</hi> and cautions, and to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves <hi>accessary</hi> to other mens sins, which they can very hardly, if at all avoid, by lending promiscuously unto all. 2. Because its usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al with the <hi>Advocates</hi> of Usury, to put <hi>stumbling cases,</hi> that are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry like to <hi>Ʋsury,</hi> and yet free (seemingly) from all oppression; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial</hi> as well to others, as the <hi>Lender,</hi> and Borrower, I shall put the next <hi>undertaker</hi> a case, which (I have heard) is ordinary in <hi>London.</hi> A poor <hi>Fisher-woman,</hi> or Herb-woman, comes to a <hi>Brok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ʋsurer,</hi> and borrows 5 <hi>s.</hi> to trade with, for that week; leaving a sufficient <hi>pawn,</hi> to return it, with a <hi>peny</hi> in the shilling, for the use of it. The woman trades with it, and turns her <hi>stock,</hi> 4 or 5 times in the week, with gain every return, with which she <hi>maintains</hi> her self and her family: at the weeks end, she pays 5 <hi>d.</hi> with, and for the use of her 5 <hi>s.</hi> and receives her <hi>pawn;</hi> and the next week does the like. Now, I ask, what iniquity or oppression, is there in this <hi>contract</hi> of lending? The <hi>Borrower</hi> gets well; the <hi>Buyers</hi> of her commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, have no wrong, but rather gain; for they are eased, by the womans fetching the fish from <hi>Billingsgate,</hi> and bringing it, to the remotest part of the City to their doors, which may justly require consideration, for the womans <hi>labour</hi> and pains: The <hi>Lender</hi> gains enough, if not too much, for after the rate of a peny in the shilling for a week, he gains but after 400 <hi>l.</hi> for an 100 <hi>l.</hi> so put out, for a a yeer: If then where there is no <hi>violation</hi> of <hi>Justice</hi> or <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> (as here seems none) Usury be lawful: why not this? I leave it to Resolution.</p>
               <p>Lastly, He laments <q>[the ignorance of some, whose zeal cries down <hi>Usury</hi> as most hateful, but make no bones of actions no less biting and oppressive; not caring how dear they sell; at how high rates they Let their Lands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not considering, that there is no less, nor less odious Ʋsury in Selling, and Letting than in Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.]</q> To which I say in a word. There may be as great, and odious <hi>oppression</hi> in <hi>Selling,</hi> and Letting; but there is no <hi>Ʋsury</hi> to be found there, which is only committed in lending of money and things of the like nature, as the <hi>Definition</hi> does import.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97861:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>